<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN" "reference.dtd">
<reference xmlns:ditaarch="http://dita.oasis-open.org/architecture/2005/" class="- topic/topic       reference/reference " ditaarch:DITAArchVersion="1.2" id="joh1441899604862" xml:lang="en-us">
	<title class="- topic/title ">Core dynamic retention</title>
	<abstract class="- topic/abstract "> 
		<shortdesc class="- topic/shortdesc ">In this mode, all core logic and RAMs are in retention and the core domain is inoperable. The core can be entered into this power mode when it is in WFI or WFE mode. </shortdesc>
		
	</abstract>
	<prolog class="- topic/prolog ">
		<permissions class="- topic/permissions " view="nonconfidential"/>
	</prolog>
	<refbody class="- topic/body        reference/refbody ">
		<section class="- topic/section ">
			
			<p class="- topic/p ">The <term keyref="core">core</term> dynamic retention can be enabled and disabled separately for WFI and WFE by software running on the . Separate timeout values can be programmed for entry into this mode from WFI and WFE mode: </p>
			
			<ul class="- topic/ul ">
				<li class="- topic/li ">Use the CPUPWRCTLR.WFI_RET_CTRL register bits to program timeout values for
					entry into  dynamic retention mode from WFI mode. </li>
				<li class="- topic/li ">Use the CPUPWRCTLR.WFE_RET_CTRL register bits to program timeout values for
					entry into  dynamic retention mode from WFE mode. </li>
			</ul>
			<p class="- topic/p ">When in dynamic retention and the  is synchronous to the <term keyref="cluster">cluster</term>, the
				clock to the  is automatically gated outside of the domain. However, if the 
				is running asynchronous to the , the system integrator must gate the clock
				externally during  dynamic retention. For more information, see the <cite class="- topic/cite "><ph class="- topic/ph ">
                            <keyword class="- topic/keyword "><tm class="- topic/tm " tmtype="reg">Arm</tm></keyword> <ph class="- topic/ph "><keyword class="- topic/keyword "><tm class="- topic/tm " tmtype="tm">DynamIQ</tm>
                                    Shared Unit</keyword></ph> Configuration and Sign-off Guide</ph></cite>.</p>
			<p class="- topic/p ">The outputs of the domain must be isolated to prevent buffers without
				power from propagating <term class="- topic/term " outputclass="archterm">unknown</term> values to any operational parts of the system.</p>
			<p class="- topic/p ">When the  is in dynamic retention there is support for Snoop, <term keyref="gic">GIC</term>, and
				debug access, so the  appears as if it were in WFI or WFE mode. When such an
				incoming access occurs, it stalls and the On <keyword class="- topic/keyword " otherprops="g.signal.name">PACTIVE</keyword> bit is set HIGH. The incoming
				access proceeds when the domain is returned to On using P-Channel. </p>
			<p class="- topic/p ">When the incoming access completes, and if the  has not exited WFI or WFE
				mode, then the On <keyword class="- topic/keyword " otherprops="g.signal.name">PACTIVE</keyword> bit is set LOW after the programmed retention timeout. The
				power controller can then request to reenter the  dynamic retention mode.</p>
			
		</section>
	</refbody>
</reference>
